# NICOLÁS URDANETA

n.urdaneta@duke.edu nicolasurdaneta.github.io (+1) 217-9795876

Last updated: July 2023

#### Profile

I am an economics PhD student at Duke University. I previously worked as research assistant at the Economics Faculty at Universidad de Los Andes, Colombia, working for Marcela Eslava on firm dynamics, productivity, and market power. I hold an M.A and a B.A. in economics from Universidad de Los Andes. I am primarily interested in approaching problems through empirical work with structural models. My current research interests are in firm dynamics, innovation, trade, market power, economic development, and applied econometrics. I also work on other projects on internal migration and displacement in Colombia and gender bias in student evaluations of teaching.

## EDUCATION

Ph.D. Economics, <b>Duke Univeristy</b> .	2022 - Present
M.A. Economics, <b>Universidad de los Andes</b> - Colombia (cum laude).	2019 - 2021
B.A. Economics, Universidad de los Andes - Colombia (cum laude).	2015 - 2019

#### Published papers

The Size and Life-Cycle Growth of Plants: The Role of Productivity, Demand, and Wedges. (2023). The Review of Economic Studies. With Marcela Eslava and John Haltiwanger. Document available here.

## Working papers

Market Concentration, Market Fragmentation, and Inequality in Latin America. (2021). UNDP LAC Working Paper No. 11. Background Paper for the UNDP LAC Regional Human Development Report 2021. With *Marcela Eslava* and *Marcela Meléndez*. Working paper available here.

"Talented" Men and "Kind" Women? Gender Bias in Student Evaluations of Teaching. (2021). Documento CEDE No. 46. (Master's thesis). Document available here. In the media: El Espectador.

## Work in progress

Equilibrium Gender Discrimination in Student Evaluation of Teaching. With Sara Ayllon, Lars Lefgren, Richard Patterson, and Olga Stoddard.

Reconciling the Effects of Migration: Do the Opportunity Costs Shape the Local Effects?. With Mateo Arbeláez and Juan Sebastián Muñoz.

## Research Experience

Research Assistant for Marcela Eslava, Universidad de Los Andes. Main research projects joint with John Haltiwanger and Marcela Meléndez (Jun. 2019 - Jul. 2022).

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Impact Evaluation for Public Policy (prof. Adriana Camacho)	2020 II
Intermediate Econometrics (prof. Mateo Arbeláez)	2020 Summer
World Economic History (prof. Leopoldo Fergusson and Juan Sebastián Galán)	2020 I
Intermediate Macroeconomics (prof. David Pérez and Andrés Zambrano)	2019 II & 2020 I

#### Undergraduate Teacher Assistant - Universidad de Los Andes

Monetary Policy and Theory	2018 II & $2019$ I
Intermediate Econometrics	2018 Summer
Intermediate Microeconomics	2017 Summer
Mathematical Methods for Economics	2017 II
Study hall for Calculus 3, Integral Calculus, Linear Algebra, and Diffe	erential Calculus. 2017 I
Integral Calculus	2016 II

#### AWARDS

Sixth place National Colombian Mathematical Olympics 30th Edition. First level category.	2011
Noche de los mejores. One of the best results in the Colombian higher education examinations	
(Saber-Pro). The award was given to 1,324 graduates out of over 240,000.	2019

### OTHER EXPERIENCE

Supuestos Economics Magazine (2016 - 2019). This is the economics student's magazine from Universidad de Los Andes. I held multiple roles: Editorial Director (2019), Revision and Edition Sub Director (2018), Communications Sub Director (2017 II). Six publications in printed edition, including two main articles. Link to website (in Spanish).

# **SKILLS**

Lars Lefgren

DIVILLO				
Stata, R & Latex	Advanced	Python & Julia	Basic	
LANGUAGES				
English	Fluent	Spanish	Native Language	
REFERENCES				
Marcela Eslava	Full Professor and Econ meslava@uniandes.edu.co	nomics Dean, Unive	ersidad de Los Andes.	
John Haltiwanger	Distinguished University Professor, University of Maryland. halt@umd.edu			
Adriana Camacho	Associate Professor, Universidad de Los Andes. adcamach@uniandes.edu.co			

and

Professor,

Bringham

Young

University.

Department Chair lars\_lefgren@byu.edu